Guide to the Morris Edward Opler papers, [ca. 1960-1996]
Opler, Morris Edward papers, [ca. 1960-1996]
- Series VI: India
  - Subseries B: Senapur Enlargement File
    - Senapur Enlargement File
      - Pictures (of People), People by Caste (alpha. by first name): Musahar (Box 80, Folder 54)
      - Pictures (of People), People by Caste (alpha. by first name): Nai (Box 80, Folder 55)
      - Pictures (of People), People by Caste (alpha. by first name): Noniya (Box 80, Folder 56)
      - Pictures (of People), People by Caste (alpha. by first name): Teli (Box 80, Folder 57)
      - Pictures (of People), People by Caste (alpha. by first name): Thakur (Box 80, Folder 58)
      - Plants and Trees, Miscellaneous (Box 80)
      - Religion, Miscellaneous: Godan Ceremony (Box 81, Folder 1)
      - Religion, Miscellaneous: Meditation (Box 81, Folder 2)
      - Religion, Miscellaneous: Worship (Box 81, Folder 3)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Dashmi (see Ram Lila) (Box 81, Folder 4)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Divali (Box 81, Folder 5)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Godhana Ceremony (Box 81, Folder 6)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Ekadashi (Box 81, Folder 7)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Jiutiya (Box 81, Folder 8)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Kartik Purnima- Ritual Bathing (Box 81, Folder 9)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Kartik Purnima- Trimohini Mela (Box 81, Folder 10)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Khichari- Sakrant (Box 81, Folder 11)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Khichari- Barley (Box 81, Folder 12)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Khichari- Decorations (Box 81, Folder 13)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Khichari- Field Hockey (Box 81, Folder 14)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Nag Panchami (Box 81, Folder 15)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Nauratra (Box 81, Folder 16)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Pitri Paksh (Box 81, Folder 17)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Ram Lila (Box 81, Folder 18)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Sankrant (Box 81, Folder 19)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Shivaratri (Box 81, Folder 20)
      - Religion, Calendrical Rites: Vasant Panchami (Box 82, Folder 1)
      - Religion, House Ceremonies: House-Beginning (Box 82, Folder 2)
      - Religion, House Ceremonies: Laying Door Supports (Box 82, Folder 3)
      - Religion, House Ceremonies: Entering (Box 82, Folder 4)
      - Religion, House Ceremonies: School Construction (Box 82, Folder 5)
      - Religion, Malevolent Spirits and Their Ceremonies: Ahir Kashidas (Box 82, Folder 6)
      - Religion, Malevolent Spirits and Their Ceremonies: Ceremonial Objects (Box 82, Folder 7)
      - Religion, Malevolent Spirits and Their Ceremonies: In Fields Due to Sickness (Box 82, Folder 8)
      - Religion, Malevolent Spirits and Their Ceremonies: Mahadev Puja- Ojhai (Box 82, Folder 9)
      - Religion, Malevolent Spirits and Their Ceremonies: Protection Against the Evil Eye (Box 82, Folder 10)
      - Religion, Mohammedanism: Circumcision (Box 82, Folder 11)
      - Religion, Mohammedanism: Moharram (Box 82, Folder 12)
      - Religion, Satya Narayan Katha (Box 82, Folder 13)
      - Religion, Satya Narayan Katha: Shivaratri- Markande Mela (Box 82, Folder 14)
      - Religion, Sects and Holy Men: Aghorapanth (Box 82, Folder 15)
      - Religion, Sects and Holy Men: Holy Men (Box 82, Folder 16)
      - Religion, Sects and Holy Men: Shiva Narayan Sect (Box 82, Folder 17)
      - Religion, Sects and Holy Men: Shiva Narayan Sect- Burial (Box 82, Folder 18)
      - Religion, Village Shrines: Offering at Village Shrine (Box 82, Folder 19)
      - Religion, Village Shrines: Village Shrine (Box 82, Folder 20)
      - Religion, Village Shrine: Women at Shrine (Box 82, Folder 21)
      - Religion, Village Shrine: Women at Shrine (Box 82, Folder 22)
      - Religion, Village Shrines: Amhit Village Shrine (Box 82, Folder 23)
      - Religion, Village Shrines: Bachila Devi Shrine (Box 82, Folder 24)
      - Senapur- General, Miscellaneous: Village Scene (Box 82, Folder 25)
      - Social Organization, Miscellaneous: Electioneering (Box 82, Folder 26)
      - Social Organization, Miscellaneous: Election- Village Panchayat (Box 83, Folder 27)
      - Social Organization, Miscellaneous: Election- Village Panchayat, Cont'd (Box 83, Folder 1)
      - Social Organization, Miscellaneous: Local Judicial Body (Panchayati Adalat) (Box 83, Folder 2)
      - Social Organization, Miscellaneous: Election- National (Box 83, Folder 3)
      - Stimulants, Miscellaneous (Box 83)
      - Women, Miscellaneous (Box 83)
      - Miscellaneous India Photos, Matted and Non-Matted (Box 83)
- Series VII: Authors- Additional Research Articles, Theories, and Abstracts
  - Bachofen, Johan Jacob (1815-1887) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bandelier, Adolph Francis Alphonse (1840-1914) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barnet, Homer G. (1906- ) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bastian, Adolph (1826-1905) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Benedict, Ruth Fulton (1887-1948) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bidney, David (1908- ) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Boas, Franz (1858-1942) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Boucher de Perthes, Jacques (1783-1868) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Briffault, Robert Stephen (1876-1949) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brinton, Daniel Garrison (1837-1899) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bukharin, Nikolai Ivanovich (1888-1938) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Childe, V. Gordon (1892-1957) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Comte, Auguste (1798-1857) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Durkeim, Emile (1858-1917) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Firth, Raymond (1901- ) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Freud, Sigmund and Jung, Adler (1856-1917) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Frazer, James George (Sir) (1854-1941) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gillin, John P. (1907-1973) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Goldenweiser, Alexander A. (1880-1940) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Graebner, Fritz (1877-1934) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Grosse, Ernst (1862-1927) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Haddon, Alfred Cort (1855-1940) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hahn, Eduard (1856-1928) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hale, Horatio Emmons (1817-1896) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hallowell, A. Irving (1892- ) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Herskovits, Melville J. (1895- ) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hoijer, Harry (1904-1976) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Horney, Karen (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Kardiner, Abram (1891- ) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Klemm, Gustav (1802-1867) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Kluckhorn, Clyde K.M. (1905-1960) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Kroeber, Alfred Louis (1876-1960) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Levi-Strauss, Claude (1908- ) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Levy-Bruhl, Lucien (1857-1939) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Linton, Ralph (1893-1953) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Lowie, Robert Heinrich (1883-1957) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Lubbock, John (Sir) (Lord Avebury)(1834-1913) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Maine, Henry James Sumner (1822-1888) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Malinowski, Bronislaw (1884-1942) (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Marett, Robert R. (1866-1943) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mason, Otis Tufton (1838-1908) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - McGee, William John (1853-1912) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - McLennan, John Ferguson (1827-1881) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mead, Margaret (1901-1978) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Meiners, Christoph (1747-1810) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Morgan, Lewis Henry (1818-1881) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Murdock, George Peter (1897- ) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Nadel, Seigfried Frederick (1903-1956) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ogburn, William Fielding (1886-1959) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Opler, Morris Edward (1907- (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ostwald, Wilhelm (1853-1932) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Parsons, Elsie Clews (1875-1941) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Plekhanov, Georgy Valentinovich (1857-1918) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Powell, John Wesley (1834-1902) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Radclidde-Brown, Alfred Reginald (1881-1955) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Radclidde-Brown, Alfred Reginald- Course Notes (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Radclidde-Brown, Alfred Reginald- Lecture Outlines (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Radclidde-Brown, Alfred Reginald- Unpublished Writings (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Radin, Paul (1883-1959) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ratzel, Friedrich (1844-1904) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Redfield, Robert (1897-1958) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Redfield, Robert- Mexico and Middle America, General II (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Redfield, Robert- Class Notes, cultural anthropology (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Redfield, Robert- History of Anthropology (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Redfield, Robert- Mexico and Middle America, General I (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rivers, W.H.R. (1864-1922) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Sapir, Edward (1884-1939 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Sapir, Edward- Linguistics (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Schmidt, Wilhelm (1868-1954) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe (1793-1864) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Smith, G(rafton) Elliot (1871-1937) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Spencer, Herbert (1820-1903) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Steward, Julian H. (1902- ) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sumner, William Graham (1840-1910) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Thurnwald, Richard (1869-1954) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Tylor, Edward Burnett (1832-1917) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Waitz, (Franz) Theodor (1821-1864) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Westermarck, Edward Alexander (1862-1939) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - White, Leslie A. (1900-1975) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Whorf, Benjamin Lee (1897-1941) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Wissler, Clark (1870-1947) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Articles- Multiple Authors (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Articles- Single Authors (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Theory Abstracts: A (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Theory Abstracts: Ba-Be (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Theory Abstracts: Bi-Bo (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Theory Abstracts: Br-Bu (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Theory Abstracts: C (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Theory Abstracts: D (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Theory Abstracts: E (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Theory Abstracts: F (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Theory Abstracts: G (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Theory Abstracts: H (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Theory Abstracts: I-J (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Theory Abstracts: K (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Theory Abstracts: L (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Theory Abstracts: Ma-Me (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Theory Abstracts: Mi-My (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Theory Abstracts: N (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Theory Abstracts: O (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Theory Abstracts: P-Q (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Theory Abstracts: R (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Theory Abstracts: S (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Theory Abstracts: T (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Theory Abstracts: T (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Theory Abstracts: U-V (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Theory Abstracts: Wa-Wh (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Theory Abstracts: Wi-Wy (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Theory Abstracts: X, Y, Z (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Series VIII. Additional Uncategorised Material
  - (Misc. Items) Decorative Square Box (Box 112, Folder 8)
  - (Misc. Items) Metal Plate (Box 112, Folder 9)
  - (Misc. Items) Elephant Figurine (Box 112, Folder 10)
  - (Misc. Items) Smaller Animal Figurines (Box 112, Folder 11)
  - (Misc. Items) Candleholder (Box 112, Folder 12)
  - (Misc. Items) Heavy Metal Figurines (Box 112, Folder 13)
  - (Misc. Items) Smaller Figurines (Box 112, Folder 14)
  - (Misc. Items) Circular Decorative Box (Box 112, Folder 15)
  - (Misc. Items) Large Circular Basket (Box 112, Folder 16)
  - (Misc. Items) (2) Large Circular Baskets (Box 112, Folder 17)
  - (Misc. Items) India- Misc. Small Objects (Box 113, Folder 1)
  - (Misc. Items) Circular Metal Plate (Box 113, Folder 2)
  - (Misc. Items) Wooden Wall Hanger (Box 113, Folder 3)
  - (Misc. Items) Wooden Wall Hanger (Box 113, Folder 4)
  - Untitled Paintings #25-27 and Painting #30, belonging to Lucille Opler (Box 114)
  - Correspondence to be filed (Box 120, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence-- A 1961-1988 (Box 120, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence--B 1959-1992 (Box 120, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence--C 1961-1990 (Box 120, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence--D 1959-1993 (Box 120, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence--E 1941-1989 (Box 120, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence--F 1963-1994 (Box 120, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence--G 1960-1985 (Box 120, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence--H 1947-1993 (Box 120, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence--I 1937-1989 (Box 120, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence--J 1968-1986 (Box 120, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence--K 1955-1993 (Box 120, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence--L 1943-1990 (Box 120, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence--M 1941-1989 (Box 120, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence--N 1973-1985 (Box 120, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence--O 1940-1992 (Box 120, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence--P 1944-1991 (Box 121, Folder 1)
  - Correspodence--Q (Box 121, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence--R 1955-1995 (Box 121, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence--S 1954-1989 (Box 121, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence--T 1964-1989 (Box 121, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence--U (Box 121, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence--V 1946-1988 (Box 121, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence--W 1915-1992 (Box 121, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence--X,Y,Z 1973-1991 (Box 121, Folder 9)
  - The Ethnobiology of the Chiricahua and Mescalero Apache.(With Edward F. Castetter) ("University of New Mexico Bulletin, Ethno-biological Studies in the American South-west," No. III; "Biological Series," Vol.4, No.5.) Albuquerque, N.M.: University of New Mexico Press 1936 (Box 121, Folder 10)
  - "An Outline of Chiricahua Apache Social Organization," in Social Anthropology of North American Tribes, ed. Fred Eggan. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1937, pp.171-239 (second edition) 1955 (Box 121, Folder 11)
  - "Ethnological Notes" in Chiricahua and Mescalero Apache Texts by Harry Hoijer. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,pp. 141-156, 214-219. 1938 (Box 121, Folder 12)
  - Myths and Tales of the Jicarilla Apache Indians. ("Memoirs of the American Folk-Lore Society," Vol. XXXI.) New York: G.E. Stechert Co. 1938 (Box 121, Folder 13)
  - Myths and Legends of the Lipan Apache Indians. ("Memoirs of the American Folk-Lore Society," Vol. XXXVI.) New York: J.J. Augustin 1940 (Box 121, Folder 14)
  - An Apache Life-Way: The Economic, Social, and Religious Institutions of the Chiricahua Indians. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1941. Reissued by Cooper Square Publisher, Inc., New York 1965 (Box 121, Folder 15)
  - "Three Types of Variation and Their Relation to Culture Change," in Language, Culture, and Personality: Essays in Memory of Edward Sapir, eds. Leslie Spier, A. Irving Hallowell, and Stanley S. Newman. Menasha, Wis.: George Banta Publishing Co., pp.146-157. 1941 (Box 121, Folder 16)
  - Myths and Tales of the Chircahua Apache Indians. ("Memoirs of the American Folk-Lore Society," Vol. XXXVII.) Menasha, Wis.: George Banta Publishing Co. 1942 (Box 121, Folder 17)
  - The Character and Derivation of the Jicarilla Holiness Rite. ("University of New Mexico Bulletin, Anthropological Series," Vol. 4, No.3) Albuquerque, N.M.: University of New Mexico Press 1943 (Box 121, Folder 18)
  - Childhood and Youth in Jicarilla Apache Society. ("Publications of the Frederick Webb Hodge Anniversary Publication Fund," Vol. V.) Los Angeles: The Southwest Museum 1946 (Box 121, Folder 19)
  - "The Role of Science in Determinating Democratic Policy," in Science for Democracy ed. Jerome Nathanson. New York: King's Crown Press, pp.118-124, 142-143, 168-169. 1946 (Box 121, Folder 20)
  - "Caste and Village Organization in a Community of Northern India," (with Rudna Dett Singh) in A Reader in General Anthropology, ed. Carleton S. Coon. New York: Henry Holt and Co., pp.464-496. 1948 (Box 121, Folder 21)
  - "Culture: The Human Enterprise," in Cultural Patterns. ("Patterns for Modern Living," Division 3.) Chicago: The Delphian Society, pp.1-39. 1950 (Box 121, Folder 22)
  - "Indian Nomads of New Mexico," in Cultural Patterns. ("Patterns for Modern Living," Division 3.) Chicago: The Delphian Society, pp.177-223. 1950 (Box 121, Folder 23)
  - "Village Life in North India," in Cultural Patterns. (Patterns for Modern Living," Division 3.) Chicago: The Delphian Society, pp.277-320. 1950 (Box 121, Folder 24)
  - "Japan: The West of the East?" in Cultural Patterns. ("Patterns for Modern Living," Division 3.) Chicago: The Delphian Society, pp.417-466. 1950 (Box 121, Folder 25)
  - "Living Patterns in the U.S.A." in Cultural Patterns. ("Patterns for Modern Living," Division 3.) Chicago: The Delphian Society, pp.517-577 1950 (Box 121, Folder 26)
  - "A Failure Culture: The Siriono of Bolivia," in Cultural Patterns. ("Patterns for Modern Living," Division 3.) Chicago: The Delphian Society, pp.773-825. 1950 (Box 121, Folder 27)
  - "An Approach to Mutual Understanding," in Cultural Patterns. ("Patterns for Modern Living," Division 3.) Chicago: The Delphian Society, pp.827-878. 1950 (Box 121, Folder 28)
  - "The Creek 'Town' and the Problem of Creek Indian Political Reorganization," in Human Problems in Technological Change: A Casebook, ed. Edward H. Spicer. New York: Russell Sage Foundation, 1952, pp.165-180. Also published in a Spanish edition: Problemas Humanos en el Cambio Tecnologico (Mexico, D.F.: Editorial Letras, S.A.) 1963 (Box 121, Folder 29)
  - India. (Pamphlet.) Fund for Adult Education 1952 (Box 121, Folder 30)
  - "India," in World Affairs Are Your Affairs. ("Publication Prepared for the Experimental Discussion Project of The Fund for Adult Education,") Karr Publication Service, pp.36-57 1952 (Box 121, Folder 31)
  - "The Problem of Selective Culture Change," in The Progress of Underdeveloped Areas, ed. Bert F. Hoselitz. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, pp.126-134. 1952 (Box 121, Folder 32)
  - "A Current Phase of Separatism in Social Science," in Problems in Social Psychology: An Interdisciplinary Inquiry, eds. J.E. Hulett, Jr., and Ross Stagner. Urbana, Ill.: University of Illinois Press, pp.205-213. 1952 (Box 121, Folder 33)
  - "Mass Communications and the Anthropologist," in Mass Communications Seminar, ed. Hortense Powdermaker. New York: Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research, Inc., pp.62-65, 97-100. 1953 (Box 121, Folder 34)
  - Social Aspects of Technical Assistance in Operation. ("Publication of United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization.") Printed by Drukkirij, Holland, N.V. Amsterdam April, 1954 (Box 121, Folder 35)
  - Foreword in Indian Village by S.C. Dube. Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell University Press, pp.ix-xii. 1955 (Box 121, Folder 36)
  - "Nonpolitical Factors Conditioning India's Asia Policy," in India's Role in Asia. ("Proceedings of the 31st Institute of the Norman Wait Harris Memorial Foundation.") Chicago, p. 70-76. 1955 (Box 122, Folder 1)
  - "The Village as an Entry to a Course on Indian Civilization," in Introducing India in Liberal Education, ed. Milton Singer. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, pp.80-89. 1957 (Box 122, Folder 2)
  - "Spirit Possession in a Rural Area of Northern India," in Reader in Comparative Religion: An Anthropological Approach, eds. William A. Lessa and Evon Z. Vogt. Evanston. Ill. Row, Peterson and Co., pp.553-566. 1958 (Box 122, Folder 3)
  - "Factors of Tradition and Change in a Local Election in Rural India," in Leadership and Political Institutions in India, eds. Richard L. Park and Irene Tinker. Princeton: Princeton University Press, pp.137-150. 1959 (Box 122, Folder 4)
  - "Family, Anxiety, and Religion in a Community of North India," in Culture and Mental Health ed. Marvin K. Opler. New York: The Macmillan Co. Chapter 11. pp.273-289. 1959 (Box 122, Folder 5)
  - "Cultural Anthropology," in A New Survey of the Social Sciences, ed. Baidya Nath Varma. Bombay, London, and New York: Asia Publishing House, Chapter 6, pp.59-72. 1962 (Box 122, Folder 6)
  - "Cultural Anthropology and the Training of Teachers of Foreign Languages," in Seminar in Language and Language Learning: Final Report by Dwight L. Bolinger and others. Seattle: Univ. of Washington, pp.90-96. 1962 (Box 122, Folder 7)
  - "Cultural Context and Population Control Programs in Village India," in Fact and Theory in Social Science, eds. Earl W. Count and Gordon T. Bowles. Syracuse: Syracuse University Press, Chapter XIII, pp.201-221. (Douglas Gilbert Haring Festschrift) 1964 (Box 122, Folder 8)
  - "Values and Education in Cultural Perspective," in Values in American Education, Bloomington, Indiana: Phi Delta Kappa, Inc., pp.115-137. (The report of a symposium sponsored jointly by Phi Delta Kappa International, Alpha Lambda Campus Chapter of Phi Delta Kappa, Boston University.) Discussion of Opler's paper on pp.137-150. Comments by Opler on pp. 28-31, 53, 64-65, 65-66, 66-67, 69-70, 73, 74, 103, 172. 1964 (Box 122, Folder 9)
  - "Cultural Dynamics and Evolutionary Theory," in Social Change in Developing Areas: A Reinterpretation of Evolutionary Theory, eds. Herbert R. Barringer, George I. Blanksten, and Raymond W. Mack. Cambridge, Mass.: Schenkman Publishing Company, Inc., pp.68-96. Also published in Spanish edition, entitled Cambios Sociales en Legiones en Desarrollo. Mexico, D.F.: Editorial Roble, pp.79-110. 1965 and 1968 (Box 122, Folder 10)
  - Recommendations for Future Research on the Processes of Cultural Change. (with Henry F. Dobyns, Allan R. Holmberg, and Lauriston Sharp). (A Report to the Office of Technical Cooperation and Research, U.S. Agency for International Development). Ithaca, N.Y.: Comparative Studies of Cultural Change, Dept. of Anthropology, Cornell University 1966 (Box 122, Folder 11)
  - Some Principles of Cultural Change. (With Henry F. Dobyns, Allan R. Holmberg, and Lauriston Sharp). (A Report to the office of Technical Cooperation and Research, U.S. Agency for International Development). Ithaca, N.Y.: Comparative Studies of Cultural Change, Dept. of Anthropology, Cornell University. 1967 (Box 122, Folder 12)
  - Strategic Intervention in the Cultural Change Process. (With Henry F. Dobyns, Allan R. Holmberg, and Lauriston Sharp) (A Report to the Office of Technical Cooperation and Research, U.S. Agency for International Development). Ithaca, New York: Comparative Studies of Cultural Change, Dept. of Anthropology, Cornell University. 1967 (Box 122, Folder 13)
  - Methods for Analyzing Cultural Change. (With Henry F. Dobyns, Allan R. Holmberg, and Lauriston Sharp). (A Report to the office of Technical Cooperation and Research, Agency for International Development). Ithaca, New York: Comparative Studies of Cultural Change, Dept. of Anthropology, Cornell University. 1967 (Box 122, Folder 14)
  - "Developmental Change and the Nature of Man," in Perspectives in Developmental Change, ed. Art Gallaher, Jr. Lexington: University of Kentucky Press, pp.17-35. 1968 (Box 122, Folder 15)
  - "Culture and the Human Potential," in Human Potentialities: The Challenge and the Promise, ed. Herbert A. Otto. St. Louis, Mo.: Warren H. Green, Inc., pp.21-45. 1968 (Box 122, Folder 16)
  - Apache Odyssey: A Journey between Two Worlds. New York: Holt, Reinehart, and Winston. 1969 (Box 122, Folder 17)
  - (ed., with Keith H. Basso). Apachean Culture History and Ethnology. (Anthropological Papers of the University of Arizona, Number 21). Tucson: University of Arizona Press. 1971 (Box 122, Folder 18)
  - "Pots, Apache, and the Dismal River Culture Aspect," in Apachean Culture History and Ethnology, eds. Keith H. Basso and Morris E. Opler. (Anthropological Papers of the University of Arizona, No.21). Tucson: University of Arizona Press, pp.29-33. 1971 (Box 122, Folder 19)
  - "Introduction," in Caste, Religion and Power: An Indian Case Study by Partap Centre for Industrial Relations, pp.ix-xi. 1971 (Box 122, Folder 20)
  - "North Indian Themes--Caste and Untouchability," in The Untouchables in Contemporary India, ed. J. Michael Mahar. Tucson: University of Arizona Press, pp.3-13. 1972 (Box 122, Folder 21)
  - The Creek Indian Towns of Oklahoma in 1937. Papers in Anthroplogy (University of Oklahoma), 13, No. 1 (Spring, 1972), 1-116. (whole issue) Spring, 1972 (Box 122, Folder 22)
  - (ed.). Grenville Goodwin among the Western Apache: Letters from the Field. Tucson: University of Arizona Press. 1973 (Box 122, Folder 23)
  - Lipan Ethnography- Miscellaneous Items (Box 122, Folder 24)